Hey, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף. daf. Well, we're getting less
ahead, which is I guess a good thing. Today where we start
with some משנה Mishnah on the top of נט עמוד ב. nun
tet amud bet. So let's take a look.
And this is something that we've seen these types of this scenario
quoted earlier and now we're gonna just play it out. So let's
take a look. מת אחד מהם. Meis echad mehem. So these two
or we haven't seen exactly this scenario, but you'll get the sense.
These two, one of them, two people, one of them became טמא
tamei and not the other.
So what they do is they enter into a little partnership and
they go because they don't know who became טמא tamei and they
go bring their various קרבנות korbanot and stipulating that the קרבן טומאה
korban tumah should work for the person who needs to work for,
right? You remember that's the first משנה, Mishnah, you know, and then
they do it over two sets of rounds because you wait thirty
days to bring the קרבן טומאה korban tumah because maybe the person
who because if you're the one that's טהור tahor you can't shave
less than thirty days, and so then you wait thirty days and
you bring a קרבן טומאה korban tumah and it works for whoever
it works for and the קרבן טהרה korban taharah works for whoever
it works for and then another thirty days and you bring the
final קרבן טהרה. korban taharah. That was the first משנה. Mishnah. Now
this משנה Mishnah says let's say one of them נעבעך nebach died.
So then the guy that's left, what's he gonna do? Right, he
doesn't have a partner anymore. Now, the easiest answer is is that
what he does is is that he's just like a normal נזיר
nazir who became טמא tamei and he doesn't get to bring the
full sets of קרבנות, korbanot, you know, but he brings, you know,
he brings a couple of them and he stipulates. Because remember, what
does a normal נזיר nazir if a נזיר nazir oh you see
here we go, here we have it, perfect, it's still there. Okay,
so here's what they do if two people became טמא. tamei. So
you bring the קרבן טומאה, korban tumah, קרבן טהרה korban taharah and
you stipulate and then you bring and then after thirty days you
bring one קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. But if it's one guy who
became טמא, tamei, then what does he do? So he waits thirty
days because you know he might be טהור tahor and he can't
shave within thirty days. And at the end of thirty days, he
has to bring something that is might be that could work for
a קרבן טהרה korban tahara and he has to bring something that
could work for his קרבן טומאה. korban tumah. Right? Because he needs
it to work for his קרבן טהרה korban tahara so he can
be allowed to shave if in case he's טהור. tahor. He needs
it to work for his קרבן טומאה korban tumah so it'll allow
him to start his period of טהרה. taharah. Okay, so for his
קרבן טומאה korban tumah he brings a חטאת העוף בספק. chatas ha-of
b'safek. Okay, which you're allowed to bring, even though it's a ספק
safek and normally you can't bring a חטאת. chatas. That's what he
brings for his טומאה tumah קרבן korban and for his טהרה tahara
קרבן korban he brings an עולת בהמה בתנאי. olas behemah b'tenai. Okay,
because that's the good thing about an עולה olah is that you
can say if I'm טהור tahor it'll count as my קרבן טהרה
korban tahara and if I'm טמא tamei it'll just be a נדבה.
nedavah.
It'll just be okay, and then and bring a חטאת chatas also?
No, you can't bring a the only חטאת chatas you can bring
בספק b'safek is the חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. Right?
So when there were two guys and the other died,
you've got to bring the whole thing because one of them needed
a full קרבן טהרה korban tahara and one of them needed a
full קרבן טומאה. korban tumah. Here there's only one guy. Yeah, so
he can so he can only bring the stuff that can work
when he's a ספק. safek. So what can work when he's a
ספק טמא? safek tamei? Well, חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, if he's טמא
tamei it works for his קרבן korban of טומאה tumah and then
he can start his טהרה tahara process. And if he's not, well
there's a special allowance that you can bring a חטאת העוף בספק.
chatas ha-of b'safek. If he's טהור, tahor, his עולת בהמה olas behemah
you don't bring the full compliment because maybe you're טמא tamei and
you can't bring the full compliment, but you can bring an עולה
olah because even if you're טמא tamei you can bring an עולה
olah as a gift. Okay, and then he waits another thirty days,
okay, and here now what he brings
is
well if he was טמא tamei earlier, he's done with that. Okay,
if he was טהור, tahor, he only brought like one of the
three קרבנות, korbanot, right? So at this stage, okay, he's he
if he's טמא, tamei, so if he was טמא, tamei, okay we
can I guess you can draw it like this. In case he
was טמא, tamei, he brought none of the קרבן טומאה, korban tumah,
right? Of the טהרה. taharah. So here he'd have to bring like
everything, which would be the עולה, olah, the חטאת, chatas, I think
there's also a שלמים, shlamim, right? Is there also a שלמים? shlamim?
I think there might be a שלמים. shlamim. I don't remember. What?
I think there is. Somebody can check. Okay, anyway. All right, anyway.
Okay, if he's טהור tahor though, he already brought the עולה, olah,
so he's only really חייב chayav like a חטאת, chatas, right? I
think, or or there might also be a שלמים. shlamim. Anyway, so
what he would probably what he would wind up doing is at
this stage he would definitely bring a חטאת, chatas, okay, it's a
postponed קרבן, korban, even if he brought started here he didn't do
all of his קרבנות, korbanot, okay, and in case he might have
done his עולה olah earlier, if he had done his עולה olah
earlier he brings an עולה בתנאי. olah b'tenai.
Do you see do you see that? Right, if I was טהור,
tahor, he already brought his עולה, olah, so now he just brings
the rest. I'm pretty sure there's a שלמים shlamim here. Okay, he
just brings the rest. And if he was טמא tamei and he
didn't bring it all, so he's also bringing the עולה. olah. So
since you don't know whether he's חייב chayav the עולה olah for
the קרבן טהרה, korban tahara, you bring that בתנאי. b'tenai.
The same תנאי tnai as earlier thirty days.
Right, if I was טמא tamei then. This is my this is
my עולת טהרה. olas tahara. If I was טהור tahor back then
then that's a gift and these are my קרבנות. korbanos. Okay let
me find out what the קרבן korban is. Okay fine. Alright so
that's what you would do. So that was what we would expect
the משנה mishna would have said. This is the first two of
them, this is the first one of them, that if one of
them died you go through this thing. That's what we'd expect the
משנה mishna to say. Let's see what the משנה mishna does say.
What does it say he does?
Oh this is
it doesn't say anything about
יום מלאות yom melos יקריב
קרבנות yakriv korbanos כבש עולה keves olah ליהודה l'olah he does not
bring a שלמים.
shelamim. I know I know I'm talking about טהור tahor וחטא v'chata
ואחר כך שלמים.
v'achar
kach shelamim.
Right so there's a שלמים. shelamim. Okay. Alright so let's take a
look. Okay מת אחד מהם. mes echad mehem. So let's read the
משנה. mishna. One of them died so they can't make the they
can't bring the full complement and stipulate. מת אחד מהם. mes echad
mehem. אמר רבי יהושע amar Rabbi Yehoshua יבקש לו אחד מן השוק.
yevakesh lo echad min hashuk. Go find somebody some stranger in the
marketplace. Maybe offer him like some money for this. שידור כנגדו בנזיר.
sheyidor kenegdo b'nazir.
And hey buddy I'm in a little bit of a bind. I
can't bring all my קרבנות korbanos because you know whatever I don't
know if I'm טמא. tamei. Do me a favor. Why don't you
agree to be a נזיר nazir for me
okay and with me right. Because here's now what we're going to
do together. ואומר. v'omer. And then he gets the guy to agree
to this. And then they come after thirty days and here's what
he says after thirty days. So he's going to be in this
realm. But he can't say if you're טמא tamei then this is
your קרבן טומאה korban tumah because if the dead guy he might
not be טמא tamei but there still won't be a קרבן טומאה
korban tumah right. Before when one of them was definitely טמא tamei
they were bringing the קרבן טומאה korban tumah and that works for
the person who's טמא. tamei. But now even if you've got this
stranger to agree you can't be מטמא metamei this guy בספק b'safek
right or whatever. Like this guy is טהור. tahor. So basically you
could so what are you going to say? So let's take right
you can't say if I'm not טמא tamei the קרבן טומאה korban
tumah works for you. The קרבן טומאה korban tumah doesn't work for
you. Right let's just read what he says ואומר. v'omer. אם אני
הוא הטמא. im ani hu hatamei. If I am the טמא tamei
good. The קרבן טהרה korban tahara מביא קרבן טומאה וקרבן טהרה. mevi
korban tumah v'korban tahara. ואומר. v'omer. אם אני הוא הטמא im ani
hu hatamei קרבן טומאה שלי וקרבן טהרה שלך. korban tumah sheli v'korban
tahara shelcha. Good
I just now have paid for your קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. This
is your קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. Did I skip a line? I'm
sorry I did skip a line. Okay ואומר. אם טמא הייתי. V'Omer
Im Tamei Hayiti. If I was טמא. tamei. הרי אתה harei ata
so here's what we're going to do. הרי אתה נזיר מיד. harei
ata nazir miyad. Look now funny sort of like the other guy
has to make this stipulation okay or I can say it and
the other guy can agree to it and say אמן amen or
something. Okay if I am the טמא tamei guy then agree to
be a נזיר nazir right away. ואם טהור הייתי. v'im tahor hayisi.
But if I'm the טהור tahor guy. הרי אתה נזיר אחר שלושים
יום. harei ata nazir achar shloshim yom. You'll be a נזיר nazir
in thirty days okay. וסופרים שלושים v'sofrim shloshim ומביאים קרבן טומאה וקרבן
טהרה. umevi'im korban tumah v'korban tahara.
You count thirty days and you bring a קרבן טומאה korban tumah
and a קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. ואומר. v'omer. And here's what you
say. אם אני הוא הטמא. im ani hu hatamei. If I was
the guy who started off as being טמא tamei right and that
when he said therefore then your נזירות neziros started thirty days ago
started
immediately. Then קרבן טומאה שלי וקרבן טהרה שלך. korban tumah sheli v'korban
tahara shelcha. Then it works perfectly right. So if I was the
טמא tamei okay your נזירות neziros started immediately. Now we're bringing both
of these. That's my קרבן טומאה korban tumah your קרבן טהרה. korban
tahara. You're done right. Everybody with me. That then works. I brought
my קרבן טומאה korban tumah that's your קרבן טהרה korban tahara we're
done.
If you brought a קרבן טומאה korban tumah
then you should have brought a שלמים shelamim too. He does. You
bring the full complement. You bring the full complement of קרבן טומאה
וקרבן טהרה. korban tumah v'korban tahara. Yeah I just didn't write שלמים.
shelamim.
I'm puzzled by some very basic thing here. הרי אתה נזיר מיד.
harei ata
nazir miyad.
Yeah. So what does he come in on day twenty seven?
Meaning you have
to wait thirty no no no thirty days from the time of
this stipulation.
So what does מיד miyad mean?
Now meaning I go up to you and I say do this
whole thing with me. כעצמו. k'atzmo. As of this moment if I'm
טמא tamei you start your נזירות neziros right now. Now we're going
to wait thirty days from this point.
So the guy needs thirty yeah okay okay. So if he was
טמא tamei and he's
if he was טמא tamei and he's טהור tahor you bring a
full complement here and you say perfect. That's my קרבן טומאה korban
tumah your קרבן טהרה korban tahara you're done. Okay and then what's
going to be at the end of thirty days? We're going to
bring a full קרבן טהרה korban tahara and that's going to work
for me. It'll be perfect. I'll bring my טומאה tumah now my
טהרה tahara after thirty days you'll bring your טהרה tahara right now
and it works perfectly right. Everybody got that scenario? That's going to
work well. Okay. Problem's going to be if he's not טמא tamei
then what are you going to do with the קרבן טומאה? korban
tumah? Yes everybody understands the issue? Okay. ואם אני v'im ani okay
הקרבן טהרה שלך. hakorban tahara shelcha. ואם אני הוא הטהור. v'im ani
hu hatahor.
Now
if I was the טהור tahor one and my the dead guy's
טמא. tamei. קרבן טהרה שלי. korban tahara sheli. This is mine. Now
remember if I was טהור tahor you're not a נזיר nazir yet.
Your נזירות neziros only starts only starts now okay. קרבן טהרה שלי.
korban tahara sheli. והקרבן טומאה בספק. v'hakorban tumah b'safek. And this קרבן
טומאה korban tumah is being brought בספק. b'safek. Now the problem is
is that you can't bring the the question is you can't really
bring the
אשם asham בספק. b'safek. We don't think so. We'll have to worry
about that. The חטאת chatas could be בספק b'safek the עולה olah
could be בתנאי. bitnai. Not exactly clear how you could bring the
whole thing בספק. b'safek. Okay וסופרים v'sofrim
but anyway that was my קרבן טהרה korban tahara your נזירות neziros
would have only started then okay now and then this the קרבן
טומאה korban tumah is just. You know it was a didn't go
for anybody but so we only brought the stuff that could work
בתנאי. betnai. וסופרים שלושים יום ומביאים קרבן טהרה. vesofrim sheloshim yom umevi’in
korban tahara. And then now we wait 30 days. Okay, those were
the two scenarios up there. ואומר v'omer. and you say, אם אני
טמא, im ani tame, if I, the קרבן טומאה korban tumah was
mine, okay, then קרבן טומאה שלי korban tumah sheli וקרבן, vekorban, thank
you, טהרה שלך tahara shelcha וזה קרבן טהרתי. veze korban taharati. That
worked perfectly. If I was טמא, tame, that was my טומאה, tumah,
that was your טהרה, tahara, this is mine. Okay, וזה קרבן טהרתי.
veze korban taharati. ואם אני הטהור, ve’im ani hatahor, if I was
the טהור tahor one, alright, so this was good. This קרבן טומאה
korban tumah was just brought בספק, besafek, so it wound up that
it was בתנאי betnai or whatever. No, it was really nobody’s קרבן,
korban, it was בתנאי. betnai. Okay, קרבן טהרה שלי, korban tahara sheli,
that would count for me, וקרבן טומאה בספק, vekorban tumah besafek, וזה
קרבן טהרתך. veze korban taharatcha. And this is the קרבן korban of
טהרה. tahara. Okay. Now that’s all lovely. The one thing is that’s
not clear, okay, sorry, is that why did this guy have to
wait 30 days to stipulate? Right? Meaning why wouldn’t he just decide
that he was a נזיר nazir here and he’d go straight? Okay.
Wait, wouldn’t he have to act as a נזיר nazir anyway the
first period? He’d have to not drink wine.
Right, right! Since he doesn’t know, he’s going to have to act
as a נזיר nazir the whole 60 days. What good does it
say to be that if I’m the טהור tahor one, your נזירות
nezirus only starts later? And here’s the answer, because remember what happens
at this stage? Not only do the קרבנות korbanot happen, but also
what happens at this stage? What do they both wind up doing?
They both cut their hair. So if I’m טמא tame and you’re...
if I was טמא, tame, then you did your 30 days, you
can cut your hair here. We’re good, right? But let’s say I
was the טהור tahor one, alright? If your נזירות nezirus had already
started and you went here, okay,
the only way you could cut your hair here as a...
if I was to... as you’re טהור tahor also, right? If I’m
טהור tahor and you’re טהור, tahor, yes? The only way you could
cut your hair is if you brought your קרבן, korban, right? Is
that clear? So if we would want to allow you to cut
your hair here and... we would have to ensure that either way
you’re bringing a good קרבן, korban, right? Whether you’re...
is that clear? Meaning if you’re... we’re going to ask you, my
friend here that I picked up in the marketplace, to cut his
hair after 30 days, yes? So if his נזירות nezirus would have
started up here, he... down over here he’d have to make sure
that he brought a קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. Alright? So in the
scenario where it’s my קרבן טומאה, korban tumah, he did bring a
קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. But in the scenario where it’s my קרבן
טהרה, korban tahara, he didn’t bring a קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. So
we’d have to bring in yet another animal, an עולה בתנאי olah
betnai to make sure he had brought a קרבן טהרה. korban tahara.
So rather than having to introduce yet another animal in order to
allow him to cut his hair, we’re going to say that if
this is my קרבן טהרה, korban tahara, your נזירות nezirus didn’t even
start yet, so you’re allowed to cut your hair here and then
your נזירות nezirus starts.
Your נזירות nezirus starts after you bring the קרבן טומאה korban tumah
so that you’re...
right, after we bring these two קרבנות. korbanot. If you were טמא,
tame, good... I mean if not you were טמא, tame, if I
was טמא, tame, good, and then this counted for you, and then
the טהרה tahara counted for you and you cut your
hair. And if I wasn’t טמא, tame, then you can cut your
hair because your נזירות nezirus hasn’t started yet.
But what good does a cutting of the hair... if it’s not
a ritual cutting as a נזיר, nazir, I don’t get it.
Because if you’re טהור, tahor, you need to do the ritual cutting.
Can’t you just wait?
No, but... but I guess you can cut his hair before bringing
the קרבן korban because his נזירות nezirus didn’t start yet. Is he
not going to bring a קרבן?
korban? In the scenario where he was טהור, tahor, his נזירות nezirus
didn’t start. But in the נזירות... nezirus... in the scenario where he’s
טמא, tame, the נזירות nezirus did start. At this stage, after 30
days, you want both קרבנות korbanot to be brought, טומאה וטהרה, tumah
vetahara, right? You’re going to have to do this, טומאה וטהרה tumah
vetahara here and טהרה tahara down there. Okay. You want both קרבנות
korbanot to be brought at the end of 30 days, טומאה וטהרה,
tumah vetahara, yes? Okay. So it... were if I’m טמא, tame, then
that works, the טומאה tumah worked for me and the טהרה tahara
worked for this guy and he can cut his hair. Okay, if
I was טהור, tahor, then that worked for me, this was for
nobody, that was בספק, besafek, okay? And this guy, his קרבן טהרה
korban tahara will be down here. Fine. But because in scenario one
when I was... when I was טמא, tame, he cut... this was
his קרבן korban and he cut his hair here, he has to
cut his hair here, right? Because we don’t know which is... which
is it. So how will we let him cut his hair here
if this is my קרבן טהרה? korban tahara?
Right. Okay.
So the answer is, if this is my קרבן טהרה korban tahara
and not his, the way he cuts his hair here is because
we say his נזירות nezirus doesn’t start until that day. Have I...
I still seem like I’ve confused people?
The phrasing is not... like connecting for me. In other words, he
cuts his hair before his נזירות nezirus actually... before we start counting
30 days of the... he cuts his hair, he cut his hair
anyway.
If he’s the טמא tame one.
If he’s the טמא tame one?
No, there’s no... the טמא tame one is dead. If I’m the
טמא tame one...
okay, so the new guy...
no the new guy... no the new guy isn’t טמא, tame, the
טמא tame one is dead. Okay, scenario number one, scenario number one
is that I am, okay, this is... Scenario number one is that
I am טמא. Tamei. Okay
and the, okay in that scenario right down here, right, it'll be
my קרבן טומאה Korban Tumah
and his קרבן טהרה, Korban Tahara, right? Right.
Okay. That's scenario number one, right? Okay, next we would have to
try to do it like this. טומאה Tumah and טהרה Tahara like
that. Okay. Now in category number in scenario number two, I am
טהור. Tahor. The טמא Tamei one is dead. Okay, so this is
me, this is him.
Scenario number two, I am טהור. Tahor. The טמא Tamei guy is
dead. So in that case, right, that I'm טהור, Tahor, the קרבן
טהרה Korban Tahara is me. Okay? Okay, yes. Yep. קרבן טומאה Korban
Tumah is goes to the is nobody. Okay, he doesn't have a
קרבן Korban here. Right. Okay. In this scenario where he doesn't have
a קרבן Korban here in this scenario, what's he doing at the
end of 30 days? Bringing the קרבן טהרה Korban Tahara and shaving.
In this scenario, what's he doing at the end of 30 days?
Not bringing a קרבן? Korban? Right? Right. So how can he shave?
I understand. He can't shave. So what we say is in case
it's this scenario, then your נזירות Nezirus only starts after you shave,
after 30 days.
I I get the sentence, but like like like I'm not a
נזיר Nazir right now. If I get a haircut, that haircut is
שייך Shayach to my נזירות Nezirus and begins after I shave?
No. No. No no no no. We're only doing it so that
the haircut doesn't violate your נזירות. Nezirus.
If your נזירות Nezirus started here and you shaved, it would violate
your נזירות. Nezirus. I understand. Now, if we're saying that the נזירות
Nezirus will start after the shave, it won't violate your נזירות. Nezirus.
So it's not a positive act of the נזירות? Nezirus?
No. It's a way that it doesn't violate, the
whole thing is the violation of once you become the נזיר.
Nazir. Right. Exactly, exactly. If his נזירות Nezirus started, then he brings
his קרבן Korban and then he's allowed to shave and he doesn't
violate a נזירות. Nezirus. If he's not bringing a קרבן Korban in
scenario number two, then how's he allowed to shave during his נזירות?
Nezirus? So the answer is in that case, we postpone the נזירות
Nezirus from starting. Now the problem still is, can I get some
context, that you're still shaving a guy that's not a נזיר Nazir
and that gets to the question we raised before about whether it's
allowed to shave and that's הקפת כל הראש Hakafas Kol HaRosh or
whatever and that was yesterday's discussion. All right. Now Genna has been
waiting very patiently because everybody jumped ahead of her, so I'm sorry,
Genna.
No, you jumped ahead. Yes.
Oh god, I'm filing a complaint.
So I have a a problem with like the whole
you have the the reason we're in this situation is you have
someone who is definitely טמא, Tamei, you just don't know who it
is.
Might be dead, might be alive.
No no no no.
Before before that, before the guy died, right,
two people and you know at least one of them is טהור
Tahor and you know one of them is טמא, Tamei, right? But
then when the guy dies,
who is the leftover guy? Is he ספק טמא?
Safek Tamei? Yes, so that's the question. Why is it asking me
to find somebody in the marketplace? Why isn't it just asking me
to do this? Right, so that's exactly the question that we're going
to that we're going to that we're going to get to. Okay?
Yes. Yes, right, exactly, once we get back. That's why I started
with this. If a normal guy is טמא, Tamei, you would just
do this process, right? So why here, right, it's really like no
different. Why here are you finding some guy in the marketplace? Now,
the benefit of doing this is that you know at the end
of the day you've brought your full complement of קרבנות. Korbanot. Right.
Here you only bring like, you know, at least the קרבן Korban
by by the end of the day you'll have brought your full
קרבן טהרה Korban Tahara here, but only partial קרבן טומאה. Korban Tumah.
Here you've brought the full complement. Okay? So that at least is
better, but not so clear because this קרבן טומאה, Korban Tumah, are
you allowed to bring all of this בספק? Besafek? You know? So
anyway, so let's take a look at, let's read the next line
in the משנה. Mishnah. So it says like this.
Okay. וזה קרבן טהרתך ואם אני הוא הטהור קרבן שלי וקרבן טומאה
בספק וזה קרבן טהרתך. V'zeh Korban Taharascha V'im Ani Hu HaTahor Korban
Sheli V'Korban Tumah Besafek V'Zeh Korban Taharascha. אמר לו בן זומא. Amar
Lo Ben Zoma. בן זומא Ben Zoma said to רבי יהושע, Rabi
Yehoshua, ומי ששומע לו שידור
כנגדו בנזיר. U'mi Sheshomeia Lo Sheyidor Kenegdo BeNazir.
Who's going to agree to this guy? To say oh yeah sure,
I'll be a נזיר Nazir together with you and do this crazy
whole little stipulation. I guess if you pay him enough money. Anyway.
Okay. אלא, Ela, here's what you do. Forget the fact that there
was another guy who died. You're בספק טומאה. Besafek Tumah. מביא חטאת
העוף ועולת בהמה ואומר אם טמא הייתי החטאת מחובתי והעולה נדבה ואם
טהור הייתי העולה מחובתי והחטאת מספק. Meivi Chatas Ha'Of V'Olas Behemah V'Omer
Im Tamei Hayiti HaChatas Mechovasi V'HaOlah Nedavah V'Im Tahor Hayiti HaOlah Mechovasi
V'HaChatas Misafek. Okay, you bring a חטאת העוף Chatas Ha'Of and an
עולת בהמה Olas Behemah and you say, if I'm טמא, Tamei, the
חטאת Chatas counts for my obligation and the עולה Olah is a
נדבה. Nedavah. And if טהור Tahor I was, the עולה Olah was
my obligation and the חטאת Chatas is a ספק, Safek, meaning I
wasn't obligated so we're going to bury it or whatever.
And there's a הלכה, Halachah, you're allowed to bring a חטאת העוף
בספק. Chatas Ha'Of Besafek. And if I'm טמא, Tamei, then the חטאת
העוף Chatas Ha'Of counted as my obligation and the עולה Olah was
a נדבה. Nedavah. Okay.
ואם טהור הייתי העולה מחובתי והחטאת מספק. V'Im Tahor Hayiti HaOlah Mechovasi
V'HaChatas Misafek. וסוף שלשים יום V'Sof Sheloshim Yom מביא קרבן טהרה Meivi
Korban Tahara and then you wait 30 days and you bring the
full קרבן טהרה Korban Tahara ואומר veomer אם טמא הייתי. im tamei
hayisi. If I was טמא, Tamei, so I haven't brought any part
of the קרבן טהרה. Korban Tahara. העולה הראשונה נדבה, HaOlah HaRishonah Nedavah,
the first עולה Olah was a נדבה Nedavah וזו חובה V'Zu Hovah
and this עולה Olah is obligatory, plus of course the חטאת Chatas
and שלמים Shelamim is obligatory, but the עולה Olah is obligatory as
well. ואם טהור הייתי. V'Im Tahor Hayiti. And if I was טהור
tahor 30 days ago, העולה הראשונה חובה, haolah harishona chova, the first
עולה olah was my obligation. And remember the reason you had to
bring it here was again to allow you to shave, right? You
had to end your... so that's why you had to wait 30
days. For טומאה tumah you don't wait 30 days, but since because
you're טמא, tamei, you have to shave, you had to wait 30
days and bring a minimum קרבן korban that would have been good
for your... for your טהרה, tahara, right? Remember that's why... is that
clear? That's why you brought the עולת בהמה בתנאי. olat behemah bitnai.
So if I genuinely was טהור tahor here, now 30 days later
I'll bring the remainder of my קרבן. korban. Okay. העולה הראשונה חובה
וזו נדבה haolah harishona chova vazu nedava and this עולה olah is
a נדבה. nedava. וזו שאר קרבני vazu shear korbanai and this is
the rest. So you don't have to try to stipulate with another
person, you just do this. You bring here the bare minimum טהרה,
tahara, the bare minimum טומאה, tumah, and by the end you finish
the טהרה. tahara. The fact you didn't bring a full קרבן טומאה,
korban tumah, okay, that's life. All right. Now again, the funny thing
here is, is this really any different? Because here too, like, you
know, if you can bring this עולה olah בתנאי, bitnai, then you
should bring it here and if you can bring an אשם בתנאי
asham bitnai you should bring it here and if you can't, you're
not bringing any more of a קרבן טומאה korban tumah presumably here
than you're bringing here, right? Because here also you don't know if
anybody is טמא. tamei. So it really raises a really good question.
Like, it's one thing to say this is way too complicated, nobody's
going to listen to you, just do this. Okay, but like what
is gained by getting the other guy, right? So that's not so
clear. Now the one thing, right? I mean, maybe it makes less...
it's not really clear what's gained. All right? Is that right?
You're bringing the same thing?
This guy is bringing a full קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. If he's
bringing a full קרבן טהרה בתנאי, korban tahara bitnai, because it has
to be בתנאי, bitnai, you don't know that anybody's טמא, tamei, then
bring a full קרבן טומאה korban tumah here בתנאי. bitnai. And if
he's only bringing an עולה olah here, then you're not gained... a
חטאת, chatas, you're not gaining anything. It's true here you're bringing another
full קרבן טהרה, korban tahara, but that's because you got a... another
נזיר. nazir. But what does that... what does that get you? You
know? So that's not besides the fact... nobody's going to listen to
you, what do you gain out of this? So that's what he
said to בן זומא. ben Zoma. Let's see what he says back.
אמר רבי יהושע... amar Rabbi Yehoshua... so here's what רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua says you gain.
Okay. נמצא זה מביא קרבנותיו לחצאין? nimtza ze mevi korbanotav lachatza'in? No,
the problem with you is that this guy's קרבן טהרה, korban tahara,
the עולה olah would start here if he were טהור tahor and
the other two בהמות behemot would be down here. So you're splitting
up your קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. So and I have you bring
your full קרבן טהרה korban tahara here and a full קרבן טהרה
korban tahara there and we don't split up. אבל הודו לו חכמים
לבן זומא. aval hodu lo chachamim leben Zoma. That was not so
persuasive. It's way too complicated in order to get over that problem.
So they agreed to בן זומא. ben Zoma. And the גמרא Gemara
says... וליתי... ulesei... and the גמרא Gemara ultimately says... and big deal,
so bring your קרבן korban in two stages, part now and part
30 days later, like what even type of a challenge was that
to begin with? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל... amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel... לא אמר... lo amar...
you mean like בן זומא... ben Zoma...
well, what type of challenge did רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say back
to בן זומא? ben Zoma? Oh, but if you do it this
way you split it up. Big deal. Okay? Big deal. What I
mean, not only do we not פוסק pasken that way, it's like
what even type of a challenge was that? אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל לא אמר רבי יהושע אלא לחדד בו את התלמידים. amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel lo amar Rabbi Yehoshua ela lechaded bo et hatalmidim.
He only said it to sharpen the תלמידים. talmidim. Now that's very
strange because normally you could say something to sharpen the students like
oh, I was seeing if you were paying attention, I'm going to
see what you're going to say back. Okay, but... but
he actually laid out a פסק psak position, right? You don't say
a פסק psak position לחדד בו את התלמידים, lechaded bo et hatalmidim,
right? So it's very strange what the גמרא Gemara means that he
said it לחדד בו את התלמידים. lechaded bo et hatalmidim. That's why
he's saying, that's why I chose this way rather than that way.
All right, so that's not exactly clear what the גמרא Gemara means
by that. And then the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב נחמן amar Rav Nachman מאי עביד ליה רבי יהושע לדקי
דלא ליסרח. mai avidei leh Rabbi Yehoshua ledakei delo lissrach. What should
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua do for his intestines that they shouldn't spoil?
Now what the heck does that mean? It's obviously some type... seems
to be some type of a slight or an insult. The first
thing תוספות Tosafot says, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says...
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק מאי עביד ליה רבי יהושע לדקי דלא
ליסרח לא איפרש. amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak mai avidei leh Rabbi
Yehoshua ledakei delo lissrach lo ipparesh. It's not clear what he's talking
about. Okay, so and then he tries to explain what he means
and doesn't read it as an expression but reads it about the
fat of the קרבנות korbanot and you'll postpone them and they... they
won't be burnt in the right time. But basically, I mean the
הרא"ש haRosh says, if you take a look at the הרא"ש, haRosh,
he says... מאי עביד ליה רבי יהושע לדקי, mai avidei leh Rabbi
Yehoshua ledakei, it's sort of opposite from the תוספות וליתי. Tosafot ulesei.
He says... הינו מעיים... hainu amei'im... oh, no, wait a minute, I'm
sorry, higher, higher, he says like
this... הדיקאמר נמצא זה מביא קרבנותיו לחצאין הכי קאמר אין אחד נודב
כנגדו, hadikamar nimtza ze mevi korbanotav lachatza'in hachi ka'amar ein echad nodev
kenegdo, one minute,
ודקי דלא... vedakei delo... הינו מעיים... hainu amei'im... לרבי יהושע דאמר שידור
אחד כנגדו... leRabbi Yehoshua de'amar sheyidor echad kenegdo...
Oh no, that's the same thing as the הרא"ש. haRosh. לאחר החלב...
l'acher hacheilev... yeah, so you have somehow to postpone the burning of
the fat, which is complicated why that... what the real... is... whatever.
Okay. Oh no, I was thinking of רש"י, Rashi, excuse me. If
you look at רש"י Rashi or Pseudo-רש"י, Pseudo-Rashi, not really רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says like this... where's the רש"י? Rashi? Yeah, like five
lines from
the... No, it says the same thing. Okay. I thought somebody basically
just said that it was like an insult, like no,
no, no, there's a note here that says that since both נזירים
Nezirim are sharing the קרבן, Corban, they delay until they, and they
have to do תנופה Tenufa together, they have to wait until they
both shave, but the delay for the second shaving may cause
the fat to be... various.
Yeah, I know, that's what everybody here is saying, but for, I
mean, the reason I didn't say it over, I gotta tell you,
is because I don't really understand it. Like since when does, first
of all, how long does it take to shave, and how long,
you know, it's like it seems like a very strange explanation. I
thought I saw somebody that said that it was basically just like
what's he gonna do that his position... I thought it was like
an insult basically, that he was basically saying
like, you know, like what's he gonna do that his position doesn't
start to smell? Like that it's that, that actually that it's like
a, you know, that he's saying something that makes sense. Like we
can't see any compelling reason, you know, to say this position. I
thought somebody definitely said, hold on. All
right, no, I thought somebody said it, but maybe I'm just making
it up in my head. All right, so anyway, to me it
sounds a little bit more like it's just saying like what are
you gonna do with this weird position of רבי יהושע? Rebbe Yehoshua?
Why should you have to do this whole big thing? Isn't it
so much easier just to do this? But the other way is,
yes, the way the ראשונים Rishonim basically explain it is that if
you do this whole thing and you got this guy בספק, besafeik,
you have to postpone it and then it's going to lead to
some problems with the fat. So anything that you gain with not
splitting up your קרבן, Corban, you're going to lose because of problems
of delays that are going to come about as a result of
this. Anyway, it's certainly not at all clear why he required all
this whole complicated mechanism. Let's take a look now at the next
משנה. Mishnah. Yes?
Just to clarify, so let's say you have this scenario where the
guy dies, right? The guy number one who's still alive, it's day
twenty-five of his נזירות. Nezirus. He goes to the שוק shuk to
get another guy on day twenty-five. Right.
So does the first guy then
have to wait thirty days?
He has to wait another thirty days from that twenty-five, sure.
Just to make sure they're,
it has to be in sync with each other. They have to
come out at the same thirty-day period. Yeah, okay. All right. All
right.
So yeah, when you said, when תוספות Tosafos asked about bringing a
חטאת, Chatas, you said he only can bring a חטאת Chatas for
a bird חטאת, Chatas, not a beast חטאת. Chatas. Yeah.
So
was there another חטאת Chatas that was not a bird חטאת, Chatas,
or it's only a bird חטאת? Chatas?
No, for the טומאה, tumah, it was only a bird חטאת. Chatas.
Yeah. There's a bird חטאת, Chatas, bird עולה, Olah, and an אשם.
Asham. Okay, now it sounds like you didn't bring the אשם, Asham,
we're gonna get to that. All right.
Okay, let's take a look. נזיר שהיה טמא בספק ומוחלט בספק, Nazir
shehayah tamei besafeik u'muchlat besafeik,
we quoted this before. A נזיר Nazir that was, forget a second
guy, he was maybe טמא מת, tamei meis, maybe he became a
מצורע. metzora. Okay. אוכל בקדשים אחר ששים יום ושותה יין ומטמא למתים
אחר מאה ועשרים
יום. Ochel b'kodashim achar shishim yom v'shoteh yayin u'mitamei l'meisim achar meiah
v'esrim yom. Okay,
so he can now as a מצורע, metzora, as a נזיר טמא,
Nazir tamei, okay, he after seven days of the sprinkling of the
ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah he can eat קדשים, kodashim,
meaning whatever קרבן Corban he has to bring to start his נזירות
טהרה Nezirus Taharah is not relevant to him becoming טהור. tahor. He
becomes טהור tahor after seven days. Okay, but as a מצורע, metzora,
he's only going to become טהור tahor after the shaving and the
whole ritual with the birds and sending them on the field and
then waiting another seven days and then shaving again and so on.
Is that clear? So, now, because this guy might be a, we
did this before but I'll repeat it, because he might be a,
if he was just a מצורע, metzora, he'd be done in seven
days. The shaving, you do the thing with the bird, you wait
seven days, you bring more קרבנות, Corbanos, you're done. But he might
not be a מצורע. metzora. He might be a נזיר. Nazir. As
a נזיר Nazir you can't, who's not a מצורע, metzora, you can't
do the shaving, right? You can only do a shaving of a
נזיר Nazir if he is a מצורע. metzora. As a נזיר Nazir
who's not a מצורע, metzora, you can't... When can you finally do
a shaving for a נזיר? Nazir? After his נזירות Nezirus is over.
So this מצורע metzora has two shavings because he might... If he
were a definite נזיר מצורע, Nazir metzora, you would shave even though
he's a נזיר. Nazir. Because he might not be a מצורע, metzora,
you can only do the shavings after the נזירות Nezirus is over.
So you wait thirty days
and you do shaving number one. Yes, clear? Now why don't you
just then say fine, but wait seven days and do shaving number
two? Because his נזירות Nezirus is over. You could say that, except
that he might also have been a נזיר טמא. Nazir tamei. And
if he was a נזיר טמא, Nazir tamei, the first shaving was
only enabled him to now begin his טהרה נזירות. Taharah Nezirus. So
you have to wait thirty days for the next shaving. Okay? So
that's why you're going to wait sixty days for the two shavings
of the מצורע. metzora. Okay? Let's draw that one.
Okay? Maybe it would be good if we do like three scenarios,
okay? If you are... If you're completely טהור, tahor, you go 30
days and you shave plus קרבנות. korbanot. We'll worry about the קרבנות
korbanot in a minute. Okay, if you're a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei,
okay, then you go 7 days, shave, and then
30 days, right? And this is and then you shave. Okay, that's
if you're טמא. tamei. If you are a מצורע metzora who's a
נזיר, nazir, all this is you're a נזיר, nazir,
okay, then you would do shave right away once your thing cleared
up, 7 days shave again. Okay, that's if you were definitely knew
you were in one of those categories. Alright. Here's the thing. Okay,
you can't shave here because because you might be a נזיר טהור,
nazir tahor, right? And a נזיר טהור nazir tahor is not allowed
to shave until after 30 days. Yes?
So now since you're in ספק, safek, you're ספק, safek,
you don't know which of these you are. So now before you
and you can't certainly shave here at the beginning because, right, you
might be a נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. So here now, the first
thing everybody's got to do is wait the first 30 days because
they might be because of this. This forces everybody to wait the
first 30 days before the first shaving because you might be a
נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. Yes? Okay. So now so now you're going
to have 7 and 30, okay, is what you should have and
now you should have shave and 7 and shave. Yes?
Yes? That's what you should have because that's what, right, because now
okay great. So now you were I'm sorry not 7, excuse me.
So now you did the shaving, this shaving now should count, excuse
me, let's do that again. This shaving should count for the shaving
of the טומאה tumah and the shaving of the מצורע.
metzora. The dotted line means the 30 day period?
Yeah, the 30 days. You had to push it all off 30
days because you might have been טהור tahor and you couldn't violate
that. Yes, so you push everything off 30 days. Now you'd shave.
That would count if you're טמא, tamei, that would count for your
first shaving of the מצורע. metzora. Great. So now let's just wait
7 days, right, and go ahead and and do the shaving either
as טמא tamei or as מצורע. metzora. Yes. Everybody with me? So
that should work. Okay. The problem is is that if you were
טמא, tamei, that's if you were טהור, tahor, and then we could
move on to that. If you were טמא tamei however, okay, if
you were טמא, tamei, this shaving now requires you, right, to I'm
sorry because I misdid it in my head. If you were טמא,
tamei, if you were טמא tamei and that counted as your shaving
of טומאה, tumah, yes, then you need 30 days before your next
shaving, right? Your 7 days here wait became had to be 30
days because of this, okay? Your immediate shaving had to be pushed
off because of this. So that now you got the first level
of shaving. But if you're טמא, tamei, you need to wait 30
days for for the טהרה taharah נזירות nezirus to do the second
shaving. Am I being clear? Yes. Jonathan, you with me here?
The מצורע metzora shaved at the dotted line also, right?
Yes, and that got pushed off. The מצורע metzora had an immediate
shaving, he had a shaving after 7 days, he was supposed to
have shaved immediately. All of that got pushed off to day 30.
But say the initial shaving after 7 days is within the first
30 day period.
It didn't happen. It had to get pushed off. It should have
happened, but it couldn't because you might have been a נזיר
טהור.
nazir
tahor. Right. So this should have happened this way, the first shaving,
but it had to get postponed to here. That's where the first
shaving got postponed to. Right. Okay, now a מצורע metzora should be
able to wait 7 days, but if you were a נזיר טמא
nazir tamei after you finished shaving you have to wait 30 days
of טהרה. taharah. Okay, so now everybody's got to wait another 30
days for the second shaving. Now the second shaving takes place at
30 days, okay. If you were טהור tahor alone or טמא tamei
alone you're done, okay. But let's say okay, you were a oh,
so why aren't you done also if you were a מצורע? metzora?
You did shave one, you postponed it, okay, you postponed this, so
you have shave two, so if you're a מצורע metzora you're right,
if you were a מצורע metzora you are done now as a
מצורע. metzora. The only thing is is that you're done as a
מצורע metzora and now your נזירות nezirus you have to worry about
your נזירות nezirus because remember the time you're a מצורע metzora doesn't
count towards your time of a נזירות. nezirus. Okay. So if you
were a מצורע metzora you're now done with your מצורע metzora and
now your נזירות nezirus starts, okay? Now which נזירות? nezirus? Are you
now a נזיר טמא? nazir tamei? It resumes. It resumes, right, it's
been held in abeyance, right? Okay. So one thing we can do
is we'll do is we would wait 30 days because it might
be a נזירות nezirus of טהרה, taharah, right? If you're a נזיר
טהור, nazir tahor, okay. So now you would do a shaving here.
Okay. But then you'd be done but if you were a... Let's
figure this out, if you were a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, then
you would have to bring, only here would bring your, you would
bring your קרבן טומאה, Korban Tuma, right? So you might be, you
might be נזיר טהור, Nazir Tahor, which is 30, but you might
be a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, which would have been seven, okay,
but because of that you had to wait the 30, and now
your last leg, you're definitely, the only thing left is נזירות טהרה,
Nazirus Tahara, and that's 30 days. So you have to do four
legs of 30 days. Okay. See, as I had a רבי Rebbe
who once said, this is what they did when they didn't have
TV. Okay. All right, so
by 60 days you're definitely out of your מצורע Metzora status. Right?
So therefore you can eat קדשים Kodshim at this stage. You're out
of your טומאה Tuma status for this for מת Meis after seven
days. Even if you didn't bring any קרבנות, Korbanot, right, the קרבנות
Korbanot are just to start your נזירות טהרה, Nazirus Tahara, you stop
being טמא מת Tamei Meis after the ashes of the פרה אדומה.
Para Aduma. So your טומאה Tuma stopped for מת Meis after seven
days and for מצורע Metzora after 60 days. So after 60 days
you can eat קדשים Kodshim and after 120 days you're definitely out
of your נזירות Nazirus and that's why you can eat you can
go ahead, exactly. Okay. So that's the משנה. Mishna. All right, so
נזיר שהיה טמא בספק ומוחלט בספק אוכל בקדשים אחר ששים יום ושותה
ביין ומטמא למתים אחר מאה ועשרים יום שתגלחת הנגע דוחה תגלחת הנזיר,
Nazir shehayah tamei besafek
umuchlat besafek
ochel bekodshim achar shishim yom veshoteh beyayin umitamei lemeitim achar meah ve’esrim
yom shetigalachat hanega docha tigalachat hanazir, you couldn't shave
when you're a נזיר Nazir בזמן שהוא ודאי, bizman shehu vadai, if
you were definitely a מצורע. Metzora. אבל בזמן שהוא ספק אינו דוחה,
Aval bizman shehu safek einu docha, but if you might not be
a מצורע, Metzora, then you have no license to shave as a
נזיר, Nazir, and that's why you had to wait 30 days and
you know 30 days and 30 days because you might have always
not have been a מצורע Metzora and you can't shave unless your
נזירות Nazirus is over. All right.
And let's just read, you know, actually it's not bad that we're
going a little bit slower now because we're now only one דף
Daf ahead. So let's just read a little bit more on the
next עמוד, Amud, but we won't get to but but we'll just
read to the two dots. Hold on, let me just read the
next thing. תנא במה דברים אמורים בנזירות מועטת. Tanna bameh devarim amurim
binzirus muetet. We've seen this before. That's when it's only a 30-day
נזירות. Nazirus. אבל בנזירות בת שנה, Aval binzirus bat shana, if it's
a year-long נזירות, Nazirus, אוכל בקדשים אחר שתי שנים ושותה ייין ומטמא
למתים אחר ארבע שנים. ochel bekodshim achar shtei shanim veshoteh yayin umitamei
lemeitim achar arba shanim. Okay, so it's easy. The 30-day wait between
each stage now become year-long waits, right? Because the reason you had
to constantly wait a 30-day unit was that each stage, here's the
real reason you had to, because when your נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara
began is the thing that forced a 30-day wait, right? So here,
here you know, I should say, so here if you were just
טהור, Tahor, you could have had a נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara at
stage one. If you were just טמא Tamei and not a מצורע,
Metzora, you would have had a נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara at stage
two. If you were a מצורע Metzora but not טמא מת, Tamei
Meis, you would have had a נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara at stage
three. And if you were a מצורע Metzora and טמא מת, Tamei
four. And those possible stages, right, is what makes each stage wait
30 days. So this is just טהרה, Tahara,
okay, this is just נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei,
this is נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor meaning for מת Meis plus מצורע,
Metzora,
and this is מצורע Metzora plus נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. So each
one of these are the four scenarios, right? You could be just
טהור, Tahor, you could be just טמא, Tamei, you could be טהור
Tahor and a מצורע, Metzora, טמא Tamei and a מצורע. Metzora. In
each one of those scenarios becomes your live נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara
at each different stage. And that's why there were four periods. So
if your נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara was not 30 days but a
year, each one of these periods would have been a year long.
Yeah? Is that clear? Yes. You look like you're yes, go ahead.
Well, I mean I'm totally lost, I have two questions, maybe that
indicates I'm totally lost.
In the way you, in the algorithm that you just laid out,
so I don't care whether the, like a ספק Safek doesn't add
anything to it, right?
Like what does the No, because if you were ודאי טמא vadai
Tamei and מצורע, Metzora, then you would have shaved right away. A
נזיר Nazir who's a מצורע ודאי Metzora vadai can shave right away.
The reason you have to wait at each stage is because if
you knew what your status was, then you're a נזיר טמא, Nazir
Tamei, you shave as a נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. You're a נזיר
מצורע, Nazir Metzora, you shave as a נזיר מצורע. Nazir Metzora. But
because at each stage you might be טהור, Tahor, you can't violate
the נזירות טהרה. Nazirus Tahara. So you have to wait till that
נזירות טהרה Nazirus Tahara which you might be in is over. So
you have to wait its full length, which is 30 days or
in the next scenario it's a year.
By the way, also and the second question was, is it was
it totally self-evident
that if I took on a נזירות Nazirus of one year,
that
by the second stage I'd have to wait another additional. whole year?
Couldn't the 30-day basic algorithm kick in?
No, because if you were a נזיר *nazir*, let's say you were
a נזיר טמא *nazir tamei*, you waited a year because you were
a נזיר טהור *nazir tahor* and you didn't want to violate it.
But now you're a נזיר טמא *nazir tamei* and you shave. What's
the הלכה *halacha*? After a נזיר טמא *nazir tamei* shaves, how long
does he have to wait? The length of his נזירות *neziroot*. And
if your נזירות *neziroot* is a year... Let's say you were a
מצורע metzora. *metzora*. After your מצירות *metziroot* of מצורע *metzora* is over,
how long you have to wait? The length of your מצירות *metziroot*.
Right? So each one of those units of waiting now becomes a
full year. OK?
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait... They could've like taken pity on him
a little.
Yeah, they could've... OK, I don't understand what that means to take
pity.
If you technically, your נזירות *neziroot*, you didn't do... you didn't do
your נדר *neder*. You can go to a חכם *chacham* and get
a היתר *heter*, but that's a different story. If you're doing your
נדר *neder*, you have to do... I mean... All right, so let's
take a look. So let's just read this ברייתא *braita* and we'll
end with that today. והיה שוהה ומטמא ומגלח ארבע פעמים ותנא מגלח
ארבע תגלחיות *v'haya shoheh u'metameh u'm'galayach arba pe'amim v'tana m'galayach arba tiglachiyot*.
OK, as we've seen. And now we're going to talk about the
קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* that you bring, and so we'll read it now
and we'll analyze it tomorrow. OK. תגלחת ראשונה מביא צפורים וחטאת העוף
ועולת בהמה *tiglachat rishona mevi tzipporim v'chatat ha'of v'olat behema*. שנייה מביא
חטאת העוף ועולת בהמה *shniyah mevi chatat ha'of v'olat behema*. שלישית מביא
חטאת העוף ועולת בהמה *shlishit mevi chatat ha'of v'olat behema*. רביעית מביא
קרבן טהרה *revi'it mevi korban tahara*. Well, that's self-explanatory, not really. OK.
So here're your various קרבנות *korbanot*. OK. So 4a...
מצורע
*metzora*... מצורע
*metzora* stage one, you have the... let's call it צפורים *tzipporim*, OK,
which are birds that you dip into blood and you... and you
send free, right? That's מצורע *metzora* stage one. מצורע *metzora* stage two,
OK, מצורע *metzora* stage two is a whole series of קרבנות *korbanot*,
but... but minimally it is a... what is it? It's a... hold
on...
He says bring חטאת העוף ועולה *chatat ha'of v'olah* and עולת בהמה
*olat behema*.
Right.
So... so right, it's a חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of*, OK, which you're
allowed to bring מספק *misafek*. OK. That's the מצורע *metzora*. For a
נזיר טמא *nazir tamei*, OK, we've...
we've learned before that it's a... you can bring a חטאת העוף
*chatat ha'of* because that's one of the קרבנות *korbanot*, right? Each of
these are קרבנות *korbanot* that you could do... These aren't the full
complement of קרבנות *korbanot*, but these are קרבנות *korbanot* that you could
get away with even if you're not in that state. The bird
thing is just some ritual you're doing with birds. You're not bringing
a קרבן *korban*. You're just dipping birds and doing some ritual with
birds. Right? Everybody knows the sprinkling and the dipping of the bird?
A חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of* is one of the קרבנות *korbanot* of
a מצורע *metzora* stage two, and you're allowed to bring a חטאת
העוף מספק *chatat ha'of misafek*. OK. A חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of* is
one of the קרבנות *korbanot* of a נזיר *nazir* who's טמא *tamei*
and you're allowed to bring it מספק *misafek*. And a נזיר טהור
*nazir tahor* is a עולת בהמה *olat behema*, one of his three
קרבנות *korbanot*, but also you can bring that בתנאי *bitnai*. Yes? OK.
So this works because it's an עולה בתנאי *olah bitnai*. This works
because it's some non-קרבן *korban*. And the other things work because they
are חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of*, which is allowed to be brought מספק
*misafek*. So which of these קרבנות *korbanot* you bring at each stage?
So that depends on what your possibilities are at each stage. Right?
What possible step... stage you might be in. Yeah, everybody with me
the point? So let's read what it is. OK. תגלחת ראשונה מביא
צפורים וחטאת העוף ועולת בהמה *tiglachat rishona mevi tzipporim
v'chatat ha'of v'olat behema*. So stage number one. What might you be
here at stage number one? You might be a מצורע *metzora* stage
one, so you're going to bring the birds, צפורים *tzipporim*. You might
be a נזיר טמא *nazir tamei*, so you bring a חטאת העוף
*chatat ha'of*. You might be a נזיר טהור *nazir tahor*, so you
bring an עולת בהמה *olat behema*. OK. You might have all three
possibilities at stage one. Yeah? Good? Have I lost everybody at this
stage?
What's the difference between צפורים *tzipporim* and עוף *of*?
The צפורים *tzipporim* is you dip the birds in the blood, you
sprinkle, you send it free. It's not a קרבן *korban*. You don't
bring it in the בית המקדש *beit hamikdash*. It's a ritual of
birds you do outside the בית המקדש *beit hamikdash*. At stage one,
you might be נזיר *nazir*... after 30 days. You might be נזיר
טהור *nazir tahor*, you might have just avenged your טומאה *tumah*, or
you might have... or you might be ready to do the first
ritual for the מצורע *metzora*.
No? I'm getting blank stares here. We can... we can pick this
up tomorrow.
The first bird is not a קרבן *korban*, it's...
for מצורע *metzora*? It's killed, it's... killed, the blood goes in a
vessel, you dip the other one in the thing. It's not a
קרבן *korban*. You do some ritual outside the בית המקדש *beit hamikdash*.
It's a טהרה *tahara* process. OK, it's not a קרבן *korban*. Think
about it like ashes of פרה אדומה *para aduma*, OK, it's a
טהרה *tahara* process. OK, so at stage one, you bring... you might
be טמא *tamei*, you might be טהור *tahor*, and you might be
stage one of מצורע *metzora*. That's what you bring. OK, we'll read
it again tomorrow. Let's just get through it right now. תגלחת שנייה
*tiglachat shniyah*. OK, שנייה מביא חטאת העוף ועולת בהמה *shniyah mevi chatat
ha'of v'olat behema*. At stage two, what might you be at stage
two? You might be... Where else might you be? You might be,
right, at stage two, you might be ending the טהרה, you're and
you might be at stage two of מצורע. Okay, I think I'm
losing everyone here.
And I was with you until about five minutes ago.
Alright, you know what, we're going to end here. Sorry to do
that mid-דף, daf, but anyway we're well enough ahead. We will pick
up with all the קרבנות tomorrow. We got the chart up there.
You'll see, it'll all make sense tomorrow. Alright, to be continued.
And I was with you through that משניות, mishnayos, but
that something...